This is actually, it's funny because I have, I feel like maybe if anyone remembers anything of my work after I'm gone, maybe don't be this image.
And it was also one of the first images I made that was not commissioned.
I spent a very long time on it, you know, Maryam Kavan, other people like were my cheering committee of like, no, this is a good idea.
I made it, I think in 2013, I finished it in June.
At a time when people who were of generations, my age and younger really, most people didn't know about Marsha.
And of course now most people do know about Marsha.
And that's as you know, because of Termalian's work.
And I knew Termalian just through at the time, like trans radical activist circles were very small.
And so we do each other.
I knew of the work she was like community history research, she was doing going and sitting in people's living rooms on their floors, you know, doing histories.
And unearthing like the legacy of Marsha and so yet and other people.
And because I followed her, I made this with her blessing.
And it was one of the first things that I made that really showed me how an image has its own life and can be part of changing history and changing the history.
And changing the stories of our communities.
It's created based on a photograph by Marsha's friend Randy Wicker, used with permission.
And it's a picture of Marsha with a flower headdress against a blue background.
And in her dress in the top of her dress, it says Marsha, pay it no mind Johnson was a mother of the trans and queer liberation movement.
She dedicated her life to helping trans youth sex workers and poor and incarcerated queers.
We honor her legacy by supporting trans women of color to live and lead.
And at the top, it says no pride for some of us without liberation for all of us.
So, you know, as it's alluded to on that page of my site, you know, these words had their own life.
And I really hadn't experienced that before.
I mean, pretty much as soon as I put out there, people assumed that the words at the top were by Marsha.
And started using them and all kinds of things and quoting them.
And, you know, that's of course, this is all what we hope and dream as artists for our work to have a life in the world, you know, and especially for Marsha to have a life in the world.
And you know, at first, after many years as Marsha, as the awareness of Marsha's legacy grew in her place and, you know, reclaimed history grew.
These words just were quoted to her attributed to our by people all over the world.
And I started feeling weird like, wait, where am I in that story?
And I realized that that really was not my place as someone who is white is committed to anti racism is trans masculine, like really the whole point of this image is to honor Marsha.
And the words have so much more power, obviously, when they come from Marsha, and I really believe that that was her spirit coming through and giving us the gift of these words.
And, you know, after some small attempts at like, you know, wait, those are by me, I just publicly was like, I, I, those are for her.
But there is a little sort of halo mark that I put in there because people did refer to her as St. Marsha.
And you know, I think at the time that I made this, there was so part of the reason, of course, that art blows up is not necessarily because that piece of art is like the best piece of art ever.
It's the context and the timing.
And at the time I made this, there was so little publicly shared trans art, there was no awareness of, there was so little awareness of our histories, there was so little art uplifting trans women of color.
And so I think people were very hungry for it. It was the right moment when things were starting to shift and, you know, also up to that point.
Any, you know, what we had as trans people in terms of the queer movement was a lot about trans people's tragedy trans people as people who are constantly killed and suffering.
And so this idea of, you know, honoring our transistors, legacies, but in their lot, you know, in life and leadership, which is now a very, I think, commonly understood shift was pretty new at the time.
So that's, I think where this was in that narrative history.
In my, in this kind of work for the movement, I always see text, it's, you see it's such a key part of my work and how we can pair down the text to work with an image to create these, to do these big lifts of radical concepts that many people are not necessarily aware of.
I'm thinking about, I just listened to a beautiful interview with Miss major, which I can send you if you want.
From the New York Trans-World History Project and she talked about, you know, how she knew Martian Sylvia and like many people found annoying at the time, but like they were, they were thinking about trans people's place in the world in political terms in a way that nobody was yet.
Like truly the lift of imagining a place for us in a world that has no place for us.
I mean, I just, I owe my life to them.